There are more than 33 health
insurance companies in India and
more than 1800 health insurance plans.  If
you are confused about
which health insurance plan is best for your family, then
after thorough research, I have
sorted out the top five health insurance plans
and done a detailed comparison of them.
In today's video, we will do a detailed comparison of those top five
health insurance plans.
Based on their features, benefits and truths.  Also we will
look at their premium and do their claim analysis
and try to understand
why I have selected only those five companies.  So
stay with this video till the end.  Do
n't miss any part.  Hello friends, I
am Ashutosh, your personal finance coach.  Let's
start the video.  Friends, the top
five health insurance plans that I have
selected are HDFC Ago
Optima, ICICI LBAD Elevat, Tata AIG
Micare Sect, Aitya Bl Activ 1 Max and
Manipal Cigna Serva. I have selected these top five health
insurance plans.
We will see why they have been selected later.
Please no one should say that if
I have a Care Care policy then it
is bad or why is Nivo BUPA not included in it?   If
I have taken these five plans then there must be some
reason.  If we
talk about the minimum and maximum entry age, then the
minimum entry age is same in all i.e. 18 years
and there is no maximum entry age.
You can enroll in all these plans at any age.
Sum Assured options range from ₹
5 lakh to ₹2CR in Optima Secure, ₹5 lakh
to ₹3CR in Elevate along with an unlimited sum assured
option.  5 Lakh to 3CR in Tata IIG
, 5 Lakh to 2CR in Activ Max and
5 Lakh to 3CR in Sarva Room Category There is no
room category
wise capping in all the plans.  And
even if there is a capping on single private AC room,
we can remove it through the rider.  Like
in Elevate, Medical Select and
Sarvottam.  Ayush treatment
is covered up to some assured in all the plants.
Pre & Post Hospitalization
6010 days in HDFC Arog Optima 9080 days in Elevate
9090 days in Medical Selection
9080 days in Active One Max and also
9080 days in Sarvottam.  Day care treatment
is covered up to sum assured in all the plants.   There
is no capping.  Organ donor cover is also
covered up to some assured in all the plants.  Domiciliary hospitalization
is also covered up to sum assured.  In all the plants.
Home care treatment
is available at Optima Secure.  Also available in Elvet.
Tata AIG Medical
is not available in Select.  It is not available even in Aditya Birla.
Available in the best.  Free
health checkup is available free of cost at Optima Secure.
ICic lambar
is available as an add-on in Elevate.
Add on is also available in Medical Select.  The Athletes Active One Max has it
inbuilt and the Best also has it as an add-on.  There
is no limit in modern treatment.  All plants have
up to some assured covered.  Second medical
opinion is available at Optima Secure.
Apart from that, Edge addon is available.  The e-consultation available
in the Aditya Birla Active One Max and the other three
plants is also
inbuilt in Optima Secure.
Edge addon is available in Elevate.
Not available in Medic Select.  Aditya bill
is available in Active One and
unlimited times is also available in Sarvottam.  Maternity
cover etc. is available in Bill Active One Max.  Also available
in Elevate with a waiting period of 2 years.
With a waiting period of 2 years, the but can also be reduced to one year.
Medical Select also offers
maternity cover with a waiting period of 2 years
which can be reduced to one year.
Aditya Bill is not in Active One Max.
And Manipal Signal Sarvam also has
maternity cover with a three-year waiting
period.  Newborn baby cover is a part of maternity.
But maternity is
not covered under HDFC Ergo.  ICIC
is covered under Elvet's maternity.  Matica Select's maternity is
also not covered.  Well, there is
no maternity in this.  And Sarvottam has a
maternity part.  Worldwide cover
is available in HDFC R Co Optima Secure.  Optima Secure and Glow,
Optima Secure Global and Global Plus
variants are available as add-ons
in ICICI Elevate, while these three plans, Medic
Select, Aitya, Bla, Activ and Sarvottam, are
not available in these plans.  You
can see the plan variants.  HDFC Ergo has only one variant Optima
Secure Super Secure in which you
get 3X inbuilt cover instead of 2X from Day One,
Global which is for emergency hospitalization
outside India and Global Plus which is for plant
hospitalization.
Medical Select also has only one variant.  The
Active One has a Max variant.
Apart from that, there is a next variant which
is available online.  The Max variant
is available offline.  This is the only difference.  And
instead of Optima Secure, it also gets 2x cover
in the next variant.  Vital
is a chronic variant of both.  If
you have any PD pre-existing condition at a
more chronic level, then you have to
take the vital variant.  The first one is a critical
illness policy.  Uttam
is a comprehensive plan and Param is a senior citizen
specific plan.  Waiting Period: An
initial waiting period of 30 days will be applicable in all three plans.  There will be a
specific waiting period of 2 years and a
waiting period of 3 years
for pre-existing diseases.
If we talk about the unique benefits of all the plans,
HDFC Argo Optimus has Secure Benefit which
gives 2x cover from Day One.  Plus Benefit
This is a cumulative bonus which gives a bonus of 50%.
Restore Benefit which gives us the
benefit of unlimited times restoration
as an add-on Protect Benefit which
covers non-medical items.
Apart from that, another add-on unique benefit
is Limitless which
gives you unlimited amount for a single claim and ABCD
cover which covers lifestyle diseases.
Similarly, in ICIC LBD, you
get the benefit of Power Booster which gives a bonus of 100%.
Lifetime Infinite Care Again Limitless
gives a claim like
unlimited restoration benefit for a limited amount. Jump Start
which covers all the
existing conditions like hypertension, diabetes, lifestyle from day
one.
Talking about the unique benefits of Two Hour Hospitalization Medical Select,
you get a 50% bonus along with the
option to take 1% premium return.
Unlimited Times Restoration
Benefit.  Unlimited
amount is available for one claim.  Same as Infinite Care and
Limitless.  Apart from that, if you
pay the premium of two or three years policy together, then two or three years are
available together.  Apart from that, there is Super
Charge Bonus which gives you a bonus of up to 500%.
Advanced cover for lifestyle
diseases like asthma, blood pressure,
cholesterol and diabetes without
waiting period.
Talking about the unique benefits of Aditya Billa Active One, it
also covers HIV and mental illness
which is a very unique benefit.
Apart from that, there is Super Reload which provides you unlimited
times restoration and Super
Credit which gives you 100% bonus up
to 500% reduction in PD waiting period.
So for normal patients there is a waiting period of three years.
But you can also
reduce the specific waiting period from 2 years
to 1 year by reducing it for 2 years and 1 year.  There
is a chronic care rider.  Which covers lifestyle diseases without PD
waiting period and Claim
Protect which covers non-payable items.
Talking about Sarvaam, there is Unlimited
Restoration piggy bank benefit which
gives you 100% bonus up to 10 times.
Sarathi which covers PDs that are lifestyle diseases without waiting period.
Surplus Benefit which provides you 100%
additional sum assured.  Like
we have HDFC Ag Optima Infinite which provides you
unlimited amount of sum assured in case of cancer, heart conditions, stroke and major transplant.  Apart from that there
is the option of deductible.
You can see the optional benefits on the screen.  Let me
zoom in a little bit more.  This is from HDFC Ago
Optima Secure.  There
are many optional benefits in ICICI Elevate.  I have made very detailed videos on all these plans - Tata AG
Medic Senior Medic Select AI Bill Activ
1 Max and Manipal Signal Sarva
and have
also made comparison videos between them.  So you can refer them.
If you do
not understand any optional benefit.
Talking about premiums,
HDFC Acco has two zones, ICICI has four
zones, Tata AG has three zones and the remaining two
also have three zones.  For premium,
I have taken the example of a 30 year old couple.
10 Lay I Assured
with Two Kids in Delhi NCR.  The premium of HDFCO Optima Cure
is Rs 30,000, that of ICICI Elevat is Rs
20,000, that of Tata AG Medical Select is Rs 27,000
but there are many discounts in it, so
after the discount the discount will be less.  Aditya
Bill Active One Max is Rs 19000 and
Manipal Singhna is Finance Gulak Rs 29000. You
can also take a 5 year policy in ICICI Elevat.  Apart from that, in all other plans
you can take a maximum policy of three years.
Now if we talk about the claim ratios of these plans, then the
incurred claim
ratio is the most important.
From this we come to know
how much premium any insurance company is charging from us
in 1 year and
how much claim it is giving against it.  So HDFC Ago has
84% ​​ICICI LBD 82% Tata AIG Medicar
Select Tata AIG Micare Tata AIG General
Insurance 76% & Aditya Birla Health
Insurance 71% & Manipal Singhna 74% This
is a very important ratio which
tells us the overall efficiency of the company.
Claim Settlement Ratio 93% HDFC 80%
ICICI 95% Tata AIG 94% Aditya Birla &
93% Manipal Cigna Talking about complaint ratio,
in 10000 claims, HDFC 15 ICICI
14 Tata AIG 10 Aditya B Birla 16 &
Manipal Cigna 25 Talking about value for money,
HDFC Aigo & Manipal Cigna are a bit
expensive.  Apart from that, ICICI Elevate,
Tata AG Medical Select and Aditya Bill are
some fair valued plans.  Friends, on the
basis of these claim ratios and the overall
experience of claim settlement,
I have selected these five companies.  If
you want, you can take a health insurance plan for your family from
any of these five companies.
But
this does not mean that if you have a Care
policy or a Nevapa policy,
you should forcibly get it ported.
Choosing the right health insurance is as important as it gets.
Our health insurance should
also be with the right company.
As important as it is to select the right health insurance, it is equally
important that we
purchase health insurance from the right source.
Try not to take online plans.  Take it
from a good advisor, a good agent
who can provide you after sales service.
If you want to take a policy with me
or want to discuss your health insurance, then you
can connect with me on the number given below or you
can book a consultation with me by visiting my website AshutoshShukla.com.
Friends, if you have any doubt related to this video,
please let us know by commenting.  If you
liked the video, please like it and subscribe
to the channel for more such informative videos.  That's all for
today's video, see you
in the next video.
Blessed